Guide to the Time Inc. Records Overview 1853-2015 MS 3009
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Records Overview
1853-2015
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009
4404.22 Linear feet
The Time Inc. Records document the history of the company from its incorporation in 1922 through the early twenty-first century. The record groups Subject Files, Bio Files, Reference Files, and Annex Files are collections assembled by the Time Inc. Archives that document the history of Time Inc., its departments, and its staff. Other record groups contain files directly from corporate offices and the offices of the editorial and publishing sides of the various publications and other departments at Time Inc. along with smaller collections assembled by the Time Inc. Archives and Library. Because departments frequently collaborated on projects and events or received the same updates via group memoranda or reports, records on the same topic may be found in several record groups or series. These records will generally reflect different viewpoints on the same topic. This Guide is an overview of the portion of the archive that is processed and open to researchers. More detailed description of the content is included in the Guides for the individual record groups that constitute the archive.
Access Restrictions
The record groups summarized in this overview Guide are processed and are open to qualified researchers. Any particular restrictions applicable at the record group level are noted in the Guide for that specific group.
Unprocessed material in the archive is not described in this Guide or in record group level Guides, and remains subject to restrictions. Requests for access to unprocessed material in response to specific research inquiries should be directed to the Curator of Manuscripts.
Accruals Note
The Time Inc. Records will continue to accrue additional record groups and, in some instances, additional material for existing record groups. Over time these additional materials will be processed and made publicly available, consistent with N-YHS's access policies for its manuscript archives.
Arrangement Note
The Time Inc. records are organized into record groups, each described in more detail in its own finding aid. See the Container List for summary information about each record group and the link to the detailed Guide for each group. The detailed Guides provide more information about the scope and arrangement of each record group, including the container inventory.
Historical Note and Chronology
HISTORY OF TIME INC.
For a comprehensive history of Time Inc. and its founders, see the authorized histories of Time Inc. listed in the citations at the end.
Henry Robinson Luce and Briton Hadden met while classmates at the Hotchkiss School in Connecticut. They became friends while working on rival school publications. Both went on to Yale University and joined the Yale Daily News as freshmen. After graduation in 1920, Luce and Hadden went their separate ways. Luce traveled, briefly studied at Oxford, and worked at The Chicago Daily News. Hadden also traveled and worked at The New York World. Ultimately both ended up working at The Baltimore News in 1922.
There they conceived of the magazine that became Time, with the working title Facts, before forming Time, Incorporated on November 28, 1922 in New York. They published the first issue on March 3, 1923 with a circulation of around 9,000. Luce and Hadden alternated as the president of the company, but shared the masthead as managing editors. Hadden died suddenly in 1929. Luce died in 1967.
Besides the flagship magazine, Time Inc. also launched Fortune, Life, Sports Illustrated, and People, along with the radio news program March of Time. Time Inc. created divisions for wider entertainment offerings such as Time-Life Books and the cable television channel Home Box Office, later known as HBO, and subsidiaries to handle the technical side of printing such as Printing Developments, Inc. Time Inc. also acquired companies such as publisher Little, Brown and Company, and lumber company Temple Industries; and publications such as Architectural Forum and the Washington Star. In 1990, Time Inc. merged with Warner Communications Inc. resulting in Time Warner. Time Inc., the magazine publishing branch, separated from Time Warner in 2014.
ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATE ARCHIVES
The earliest documentation regarding the establishment of the Time Inc. Archives dates from 1941, when a proposal was sent to one of the company's top executives, stating, "We are in favor of starting a confidential file of Archives, which can be kept up to date and which, as time goes on, should prove invaluable for...a comprehensive history of the company...Things we'd like to save: original dummies, prospectuses, and first copies of all the magazines, complete sets of annual reports, complete and up to date material on H.R.L. and his writings, a complete set of all company bulletins, pictures, diaries and personal accounts of all early employees, etc...But there is at present, so far as I know, no systematic effort to keep track of all documents which have long range value to the company...Main thing I am anxious to establish is the habit of saving valuable material. If you approve the project, we can start delving almost at once."
In 1950, after passing through the hands of several long time employees, the Archives Department was formally established, reporting up to the company's Central Services division.
REASON FOR ESTABLISHING ARCHIVES
One of the guiding reasons for establishing the Archive was, as noted above, that as early as 1941, Time Inc. was considering a "comprehensive history of the company." A memo in an Archives folder in the Reference Files, from April 1950, expresses the desire for a "definitive, scholarly history of Time Inc." Three authorized histories have been published so far:
Elson, Robert T. 1968. Time, Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum.
Elson, Robert T., and Duncan Norton-Taylor. 1973. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1941-1960. New York: Atheneum.
Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
According to Robert T. Elson, "Luce had a very strong sense of history, and a feeling that Time Inc. was a unique institution. What he wanted was a record of the men and women who worked there."
Chronology
1922 Initial business offices are in 141 East 17th Street, then move to the Printing Crafts Building at 461 Eighth Avenue.
1922 November Henry R. Luce and Briton Hadden incorporate in New York as Time, Incorporated.
1922 December First officers are elected: President, Hadden; Secretary and Treasurer, Luce; Vice President, to be determined. First directors of the board are elected: E. R. Crowe, Henry P. Davison, Jr., William V. Griffin, Hadden, and Luce. Offices secured at 9 East 40th Street, 9th Floor.
1923 March First issue of Time is released.
1923 April Obtain new offices at 236 East 39th Street.
1924 May Began publishing Saturday Review of Literature, a renewal of the Literary Review formerly in the New York Post. The first issue is released in August.
1925 August Publishing headquarters move from New York City to Cleveland.
1926 January The Saturday Review of Literature separates from Time Inc.
1926 February New election of officers: Chairman of the Board and President, Luce; Vice President, Treasurer and Secretary, Hadden.
1926 October Davison suggests filling a vacancy in the board with a woman. Hadden rejects the idea.
1927 January Time begins the transition from a black-and-white cover to a color cover.
1927 April Prints the first issue of Tide, an in-house monthly newsletter "dedicated to the flow of business".
1927 August Editorial Department moves from Cleveland to New York City followed later by the General Manager Office, Accounting Department, and Advertising Promotional Department. Editorial temporarily have offices at 25 West 45th Street.
1928 Begin production of a daily 10-minute radio feature called "Newscasting" supplied to 60 radio stations. Names first "Man of the Year."
1928 January Production Department moves from Cleveland to Chicago. Publishes first issue of Tide as a subscription trade journal. Robert L. Johnson and Roy E. Larsen are added as vice presidents.
1928 July Circulation Department moves from Cleveland to Chicago, although the circulation promotion manager relocates to New York City a month later.
1928 October Move from temporary offices into the Bartholomew Building on East 42nd Street.
1929 February Hadden dies on February 27 after contracting the flu and then developing a blood stream infection.
1929 March Larsen becomes general manager after Hadden's death. New election of officers: Chairman of the Board and President, Luce; Vice Chairman, Griffin; Vice President and Secretary, Johnson; Vice President and Secretary, Larsen; Assistant Treasurer, Charles L. Stillman. John S. Martin becomes managing editor of Time after Hadden's death.
1930 Sells Tide to a group headed by Raymond Rubicam.
1930 February Publishes first issue of Fortune with Parker Lloyd-Smith as managing editor.
1931 March The March of Time debuts on March 6, 1931 as radio newsreel on CBS Radio.
1931 August Move offices to the Chrysler Building.
1931 September Ralph Ingersoll takes over as managing editor of Fortune after Lloyd-Smith's death.
1932 April Acquires building journal Architectural Forum.
1933 July The company issues a memo removing the comma between "Time" and "Incorporated."
1934 January Publishes first issue of Letters, a supplement to accommodate the overflow of letters to the editor. Letters continues through 1937.
1935 February First release of The March of Time movie short at the Capitol Theatre in New York City on February 1, 1935.
1935 August Ingersoll named general manager of Time Inc. Eric Hodgins named managing editor of Fortune.
1936 Purchases a publication entitled Life in order to use the name for the new picture magazine.
1936 November Publishes first issue of Life.
1937 Manfred Gottfried (the first writer hired) named managing editor of Time.
1937 March Hodgins named publisher of Fortune. Ingersoll named publisher of Time. Larsen named publisher of Life.
1938 April Move offices to the Time & Life Building at 9 Rockefeller Plaza.
1939 Implements initial employee profit-sharing plan.
1939 June Time is the first to use the terms "World War I" and "World War II."
1939 September Luce resigns as president and chief operating officer in order to focus on the company's editorial direction, remaining editor-in-chief and board chairman. Larsen is elected to take over as president and CEO.
1942 M. T. Moore elected chairman of the board.
1942 November Clare Boothe Luce, wife of Henry Luce, elected Connecticut representative for U.S. Congress.
1943 January T. S. Matthews named managing editor of Time.
1944 June Daniel Longwell named managing editor of Life. John Shaw Billings named editorial director of Time.
1945 James A. Linen named publisher of Time. Purchases Michigan Square Building in Chicago.
1946 Holds dinner party in New York for guest of honor Winston Churchill. Gottfried named chief of correspondents for Time and Life international bureaus.
1946 January Andrew Heiskell named publisher of Life.
1946 October Joseph Thorndike named managing editor of Life.
1949 August Edward Thompson named managing editor of Life.
1951 August The March of Time ceases production.
1952 Architectural Forum is split into two magazines: Forum for commercial buildings, and House & Home for residential. Purchase first television station: KOB in Alburquerque, NM. Begin construction of Time & Life Building in London.
1953 Publishes first foreign language magazine: Life En Español.
1954 August Publishes first issue of Sports Illustrated.
1956 December Announce plans to construct a new Time & Life Building at the Rockefeller Center.
1959 July Hedley Donovan named editorial director.
1960 Heiskell named chairman of the board.
1961 January Establishes the Book Division with Jerome Hardy as publisher and Norman Ross as editor.
1961 June Establishes Time-Life Broadcast Inc.
1961 September Time Life International and Life International suspend all subscriptions to Cuba.
1961 November Life En Español banned in Spain due to article on Spanish Civil War.
1962 Acquires textbook publisher Silver Burdett. Publishes first issue of Panorama, a joint venture with Italian publisher Arnoldo Mondadori Editore.
1962 March Time launches a New York Metropolitan Edition.
1963 Time conducts the first newstour. Book Division renamed Time-Life Books.
1964 April Luce names Donovan as the editor-in-chief. Luce steps down as editor-in-chief. He is now the editorial chairman.
1964 August An August/September double issue is the last issue of Architectural Forum produced by Time Inc. McGraw Hill takes over publishing House & Home.
1964 November Time Inc. History Project launches overseen by Robert Elson.
1964 December The American Planning and Civic Association acquire Architectural Forum.
1965 Receives Special Merit award from the U.S. Post Office for David Brumbaugh's contributions to improving the zoning system (ZIP codes).
1966 December Acquires the New York Graphic Society as a new subsidiary of the Books Group.
1967 February Luce dies on February 28 from heart attack.
1968 Construction completed on Time & Life Building at 541 North Fairbanks Court in Chicago. This location houses the Subscription Services Division. Henry "Hank" Luce III named publisher of Fortune.
1968 January Acquires the publisher Little, Brown and Company.
1968 May Otto Fuerbringer named "chief explorer of Time Inc.'s interests and opportunities in the newspaper field."
1969 Luce III named publisher of Time.
1969 March Acquires Pioneer Publishing Company.
1969 September Creation of the Time-Life Films Division.
1970 Joan Manley named publisher of Time-Life Books, the first woman to hold a publisher position at Time Inc.
1970 October Time-Life radio and television properties acquired by McGraw Hill.
1970 December Life International publishes final issues. Time-Life Audio Division created.
1971 Manley elected vice president, the first woman vice president at Time Inc.
1971 July George Hunt named editor of Time-Life Films.
1972 Founds the Home Box Office (HBO). Ralph P. Davidson named publisher of Time. Publishes first issue of Money. Acquires collection of photographs from New York City photo bureau Pix Inc.
1972 December Suspends the publication of Life.
1973 Time Editorial and the News Service merge. Manhattan Cable TV becomes a wholly-owned subsidiary.
1974 March Publishes first issue of People.
1974 July Time establishes the title of Senior Writer.
1976 April Ralph Graves named corporate editor.
1976 July Edward Jamieson named Time executive editor.
1977 July Acquires Book of the Month Club (BoMC) as a subsidiary of the Books Group. Dick Armstrong and Paul Finney named Fortune executive editors.
1977 December American Television and Communications Corporation (ATC) becomes a subsidiary.
1978 Time donates original cover art collection to the National Portrait Gallery. Revives Life as a monthly publication.
1978 January Fortune becomes a biweekly publication.
1978 September Jason McManus named executive editor of Time.
1979 June Donovan retires and recommends Henry Grunwald as his successor editor-in-chief.
1979 July Graves named editorial director.
1980 Publishes first issue of Discover. Davidson named chairman of Time Inc.
1980 October J. Richard Munro named chief executive officer (CEO).
1981 January Time Inc. Series C preferred stock offered to public.
1981 March Sells Time-Life Films to Columbia Pictures.
1981 June Purchases transponders on Hughes Galaxy I satellite for HBO use.
1982 Establishes the Heiskell Award which was presented to Time Inc. employees "who have made an exceptional contribution in the areas of public service, human rights and equal opportunity."
1982 August N. J. Nicholas, Jr. named chief financial officer (CFO).
1982 October Reginald Brack named president of Time-Life Books.
1984 October Michael J. Fuchs named chairman and CEO of HBO.
1987 Grunwald retires as editor-in-chief, and McManus is appointed as successor. Sells Discover to Family Media.
1989 Time Inc. and Warner Communications Inc. announced plan to merge.
1989 April Louis A. "Chip" Weil becomes Time publisher.
1990 February Publishes first issue of Entertainment Weekly.
Citations:
"American's Mailing Industry: Powered by the United States Postal Service. Time Inc." National Postal Museum. Accessed on December 5, 2016. http://postalmuseum.si.edu/americasmailingindustry/Time-Inc.html
"Briton Hadden Dies; An Editor of Time." The New York Times. February 28, 1929.
Elson, Robert T. 1968. Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum.
Elson, Robert T., and Duncan Norton-Taylor. 1973. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1941-1960. New York: Atheneum.
Kaufman, Leslie. "Time Inc. to Cut 500 Jobs Ahead of Spinoff." The New York Times. February 4, 2014. Accessed June 14, 2016. http://www.nytimes.com/2014/02/05/business/media/time-inc-announces-layoffs-as-it-prepares-to-go-public.html
Langer, Emily. "Ralph P. Davidson, Former Chairman of Time Inc. and Kennedy Center, Dies at 86." The Washington Post. August 2, 2014. Accessed December 6, 2016. https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/obituaries/ralph-p-davidson-former-chairman-of-time-inc-and-kennedy-center-dies-at-86/2014/08/02/905dfed4-166f-11e4-9e3b-7f2f110c6265_story.html
"Manfred Gottfried, 85, Dies: A Former Co-editor of Time." The New York Times. September 21, 1985. Accessed December 6, 2016. http://www.nytimes.com/1985/09/21/nyregion/manfred-gottfried-85-dies-a-former-co-editor-of-time.html
Norrismarch, Floyd. "Time Inc. and Warner to Merge, Creating Largest Media Company." The New York Times. March 5, 1989.
Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
"The TIME Collection." National Portrait Gallery (Smithsonian Institution). http://npg.si.edu/portraits/time-magazine-portraits-collection
"Time's Film Unit Sold to Columbia." Business section. The New York Times. August 13, 1981. Accessed January 18, 2018. http://www.nytimes.com/1981/08/13/business/time-s-film-unit-sold-to-columbia.html
"A Timeline of Time Warner Inc." Wall Street Journal. July 16, 2014. Accessed June 14, 2016. http://www.wsj.com/articles/a-timeline-of-time-warner-inc-1405522663
Whitman, Alden. "Henry R. Luce, Creator of Time-Life Magazine Empire, Dies in Phoenix at 68." The New York Times. March 1, 1967. Accessed June 14, 2016. http://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/bday/0403.html
Related Archival Materials Note
The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Scope and Contents Note
The Time Inc. Records document the history of the company from its incorporation in 1922 through the early twenty-first century. Because departments frequently collaborated on projects and events or received the same updates via group memoranda or reports, records on the same topic may be found in several record groups or series. These records will generally reflect different viewpoints on the same topic. Records throughout the collection frequently use the shorthand "34th" to refer to the corporate level offices whcih were on the 34th floor of the Manhattan Time & Life Building, and "541" to refer to the Chicago Time & Life Building.
The four major record groups that document the history of the company as a whole include the Subject Files, created as a reference tool for the writers of authorized histories of Time Inc., focusing on the areas of corporate, editorial, and publishing; the Bio Files documenting the careers of Time Inc. staff, non-staff closely associated with the company, and notable figures; the Reference Files, originally Time Inc.'s central file, documenting the history of various Time Inc. divisions, franchises, and staff organizations, along with runs of staff newsletters; and the Annex Files, an extension of the types of records kept in the Subject Files, but not part of that record group.
Additional record groups that relate to the entire company include the Corporate Administration Records containing files from the corporate-level offices and executives of Time Inc. as well as stock certificates, five-year plans, notary seals, patents, printing agreements, and organizational records from affiliates and subsidiaries; the New Building Department Records documenting the design, construction, and furnishing of the Time & Life Building at Rockefeller Center; the Administration, Human Resources and Personnel Records documenting employee relations, benefits, and personnel policies; Staff Organizations documenting membership organizations involving only Time Inc. staff; the Real Estate Division Records on building and land purchases, construction, and alternations for offices and other facilities of Time Inc. and its subsidiaries; Corporate Public Affairs Department Records documenting the promotion of Time Inc. through newstours, radio and television appearances, community projects, and speeches to groups in the publishing arena; the Time Inc. Annual Reports documenting the creation of new departments and new ventures; transcripts and recordings of staff interviews from an oral history project undertaken by the Time Inc. Archives; files from the Production Department about the supply of paper products and the subsidiary the East Texas Pulp and Paper Company (Eastex); files on the creation of a new corporate logo and trademark; the Corporate Circulation Records documenting the marketing of subscriptions for all of the company's magazines; the Travel Services Records regarding business travel arrangements for Time Inc. employees; the Company Services Records containing flight logs of an aircraft owned by Time Inc. and invoices for purchase of various items of office furniture and equipment; the records of the Comptroller documenting the accounting and financial reporting for the whole company; the realia collected by the Time Inc. Archives documenting branded material created by Time Inc. or awards received by Time Inc.; Time Inc.'s corporate identity rebranding; and Time Inc. International records documenting Time Inc.'s publishing efforts outside of the United States.
Records groups from the editorial side of Time Inc. may include files from a magazine's managing editors, executive editors, and art departments. Of note are the Corporate Editorial Records, a department overseeing all publications at Time Inc. and containing files from Editors-in-Chief Donovan Hedley, Henry Grunwald, and Jason McManus; and the Magazine Development Group's work on designing and launching new magazines.
Other editorial record groups include Time Editorial Records; Fortune Editorial Records; Life Editorial Records; People Editorial Records; Money Editorial Records; Architectural Forum and House & Home Editorial Records; Sports Illustrated Editorial Records; and Sports Illustrated for Kids Records. Additional records regarding Time include a chronological run of covers and bound and annotated issues.
Reference materials used by editorial staff include the Index Cards containing groups of index cards used for searching and cross referencing subject terms in Time Inc.'s major magazines; and files on people, presidents, and subjects from the Time Research Center.